So in this class this semester,
于是在本学期的这门课里，
I'm making three big predictions, right?
我做了三个大预测，对吧？
First is that Trump will win in November.
第一个是特朗普将在十一月赢得选举。
Second is that
第二个是……
United States will go to war against Iran.
美国将对伊朗发动战争。
The third big prediction is that
第三个大预测是……
United States will lose this war,
美国将在这场战争中失败，
which will forever change the global order.
These past, so
last class we looked at one reason why the United States would invade Iran,
上一节课我们讨论了美国入侵伊朗的一个原因，
which is the Israel lobby.
那就是以色列游说。
And in today's class, we'll look at another reason,
今天的课我们再来看看一个原因，
which is the defense of empire.
那就是帝国的防御。
America is an empire and
美国是一个帝国，
it must defend its imperial status.
它必须守护其帝国地位。
So let's examine what an empire means for America.
于是我们来看看帝国对美国意味着什么。
So from 1950 to 1980,
于是从1950年到1980年，
America's economy was mainly focused on manufacturing,
美国经济主要聚焦于制造业，
factories, okay?
工厂，好的？
So manufacturing as a share of GDP was 40%.
于是制造业占国内生产总值的40%。
It made 40% of profits, okay?
它占利润的40%，好吧？
And it employed 30% of the workforce.
并且它雇佣了30%的劳动力。
So during World War II,
于是在第二次世界大战期间，
America had a lot of factories to produce weapons.
美国拥有大量工厂来生产武器。
And after World War II,
[25] 于是第二次世界大战结束后，
these factories produced consumer goods,
[26] 这些工厂生产了消费品。
cars, electronics to sell to the world.
汽车、电子产品销往世界。
And this made the American workers
这让美国工人……
the wealthiest and
最富裕的
most well -educated middle class ever in human history.
最受过教育的中产阶层
If you were a factory worker from 1950 to 1980,
如果你是1950到1980年的工厂工人，
you had a really good life.
你就过着相当不错的生活。
You worked 40 hours a week.
你每周工作40小时。
You had health insurance. You could buy your own house.
你有健康保险，可以买自己的房子。
Your wife didn't have to work.
你的妻子不必工作。
You could have three to four kids.
你可以有三四个孩子。
You could have two cars.
你可以拥有两辆车。
Every year, you could go on vacation to some place nice.
每年你都能去一个好地方度假。
You could eat out once a week.
你每周可以外出吃一次饭。
And then you retire and have a very good pension.
然后你退休，拿到一笔不错的养老金。
So it was really the best life.
于是这才是最好的生活。
And so workers, they had to work.
于是工人们就得去工作。
And so, from 1950, 1980, in America,
于是，从1950年到1980年，在美国，
were really the luckiest people on the planet.
他们真是地球上最幸运的人。
You were better off, actually,
你实际上更好一点。
being born into the middle
出生在中产阶层
class in America than you were being born rich in Africa,
在美国的阶级比你在非洲出生时的富裕阶级更好
or Asia, or South America, okay?
或亚洲，或南美，行吗？
But then, after 1980, was something called the Reagan Revolution,
但随后，1980年以后出现了所谓的里根革命
and the introduction of, what we call, neoliberalism,
以及我们所说的自由主义的引入，
And remember that we studied neoliberalism before.
并且记得我们之前学过新自由主义。
Neoliberalism is an economic philosophy
新自由主义是一种经济哲学
that believes in the primacy of free markets
它相信自由市场的首要性
and deregulation.
和去监管。
So after that,
于是之后，
we now live in today what we call a financial economy.
我们现在生活在我们所说的金融经济时代。
The economy has been financialized.
经济已被金融化。
And so what does that mean?
于是这意味着什么？
It means that right now,
它意味着现在正是……
financial services account
金融服务占比
for 22% of all GDP in America.
在美国占国内生产总值的22%。
Manufacturing has gone down to 10%.
制造业已降至10%。
So it went down from a high of 40% to now a low of 10%.
它从高点的40%降至现在的10%。
Financial services is now twice as much as manufacturing.
金融服务现在是制造业的两倍。
Financial services bring in 40%.
金融服务贡献了40%。
Of all.
全部
Profits. And
利润。还有
financial services employs 5%.
金融服务业雇佣5%。
Of the total American workforce.
美国总劳动力中
Okay? Now, let me explain what these numbers mean.
好的？现在，我来解释这些数字的含义。
What you're seeing behind these
你在这些背后看到的
numbers is a radical shift,
数字显示出一次根本的转变
overhaul, transition in American society.
大改造，社会转型
Let's just look at politics.
让我们先看政治
Politics. Governance. From this period,
政治。治理。从这一时期开始，
1950 to 1980, American workers had a lot of political power.
1950到1980年，美国工人拥有大量政治权力。
Because they were middle class, they were confident,
因为他们是中产阶层，充满自信。
they participated in politics for unions.
他们参与工会政治。
Today, most of this power has shifted to the financial services.
如今，这股力量大多已转移至金融服务业。
Which basically means Wall Street.
这基本就是指华尔街。
And that means the economy. And
这又意味着经济。
working for Wall Street are what
在华尔街工作的就是
we call the
我们称之为
professional managerial
专业管理的
elite.
精英的
Okay? So these are people who live on the coast.
好的？所以这些人住在海岸上。
San Francisco, New York, Washington, DC, Boston.
旧金山、纽约、华盛顿特区、波士顿。
They went to elite schools.
他们就读了名校。
Okay? The Ivy League.
好？就是常春藤。
And they're multicultural.
而且他们是多元文化的。
And right now, they're the most popular.
现在正是他们最受欢迎的时候。
They're the most powerful political group in America.
他们是美国最有影响力的政治团体。
And this has led to massive political divisions within the country.
这导致了国内大规模的政治分裂。
Okay? So it's the first major consequence.
好？这就是第一个主要后果。
Before, it was workers who
之前是工人有大影响力。
had a large say over American politics.
他们在美国政治中有大话语权。
And now it is Wall Street, the financial sector,
现在是华尔街，金融部门，
and the coastal professional management elite.
以及沿海岸的专业管理精英。
And so government shapes policies that
于是政府制定政策。
favors the political system.
倾向政治体系。
And so we have this multicultural elite, financial elite,
于是我们拥有了这支多元文化的精英，金融精英，
over at the expense of workers.
在工人之支出费的情况下。
Okay? So that's the first major shift.
好的？这就是第一个主要转变。
But then you look at education.
然后你再看看教育。
And so what I mean by that is that, you know,
所以，我的意思是这样的，你知道，
if you went to a good school, a good university in the 1950s and
如果你在1950年代去了一所好学校，好大学，
1960s, your ambition was to become a professor.
1960年代，你的目标是成为教授。
Right? Or maybe a scientist.
对吧？或者是科学家。
Or maybe an entrepreneur.
或者是企业家。
Or a corporate executive.
或者是企业高管。
Okay? Nowadays,
好的？现在，
most people who
大多数人都
graduate from these top schools all want to go where?
毕业于这些顶尖学校后都想去哪里？
Wall Street. And that's it.
华尔街。就这么简单。
Okay? Why? Because you make more money on Wall Street than anywhere else.
好的？为什么？因为你在华尔街能赚的钱比其他地方多。
Okay? So you're talking about these PhDs in statistics
好的？所以你在说这些统计学和人工智能的博士。
and artificial intelligence who should be working in the field.
他们本该在该领域工作。
They should be working for IBM,
他们本该在 IBM 工作，
developing the latest technology.
研发最新技术。
Right? Instead, they're on Wall Street working for a hedge fund,
对吧？结果他们在华尔街为对冲基金工作，
gambling with other people's money.
用别人的钱赌博。
Okay? So basically the economy has gone from one
好吧？所以基本上经济已经从一种
that is productive or
有生产力的或
creative to one that is entirely speculative.
创意变成完全投机的。
Okay? So remember that the financial services,
好吧？记住金融服务，
all it does is take people's money and
它所做的就是拿人家的钱并且。
gamble with it or invest in it to make more money.
用它赌博或投资赚更多钱。
Okay? It's not actually productive. All it is is speculative.
好吧？它其实并不生产，只是投机。
Okay? And the smartest people in America,
好吧？而美国最聪明的人们，
the most well -educated, are all focused on this sector.
最受过教育的人们都聚焦于此行业。
Okay? And then
好吧？然后
you look at the economy.
你再看经济。
Okay? And
好吧？而且
what has clearly changed is that
明显改变的是
the economy in America has become much more unstable.
美国经济变得更不稳定。
So in 2001, there was the Internet crash.
于是2001年出现了互联网泡沫。
Right? The dot -com crash. In 2008,
对吧？点com泡沫。2008年，
there was the financial crisis.
出现了金融危机。
Right? The subprime crash.
对吧？次贷危机。
And then after that, you have all the, you have these banks going bankrupt.
然后接着那样，你就会看到这些银行相继破产。
Okay? I think like this past week, three banks went bankrupt in America.
对吧？我想过去一周里，美国就有三家银行倒闭了。
This should not be happening.
这本该不会发生。
And the reason why this is happening are all these bubbles.
而导致这一切发生的原因就是这些泡沫。
Okay? So in other words,
好的？换句话说，
all assets right now in America overpriced.
现在美国所有资产都被高估。
Okay? Housing, stock market,
好的？住房、股市，
and people are gambling
人们在赌盘
that these asset prices will go higher, which creates bubbles.
这些资产价格会进一步上涨，形成泡沫。
And when these bubbles burst, you have volatility and instability.
当泡沫破裂时，就会出现波动和不稳定。
And uncertainty. Okay?
还有不确定性。好的吗？
So this is bad for the economy.
这对经济来说是坏事。
And then you have things like inequality.
然后出现了诸如不平等的情况。
Right? So
对吧？所以
if you look at profits, if you look at wealth generation,
如果你看利润，如果你看财富创造，
the top 1% make much more money than everyone else.
前1%赚的钱比其他人多得多。
And this inequality is only increasing.
这种不平等只会越来越大。
Okay? So in other words, you have this inequality. Well, first,
好的？换句话说，就是出现了不平等。
the financialization of the American economy
美国经济的金融化
has been really bad for America.
已经对美国造成了很大影响。
And you can make the argument that it's actually destroying the fabric of American society.
可以说它正是破坏美国社会结构的根基。
Okay? It's making politics much more divisive.
好吧？它让政治更分裂。
It's making the economy much more volatile.
它让经济更波动。
The smartest people are engaged in speculative activities.
最聪明的人从事投机活动。
Young people don't want to work.
年轻人不想工作。
They just want to buy Bitcoin. coin. And
他们只想买比特币。
you can also make the argument that
你也可以说……
you're creating a rentier economy.
你正在创造租赁经济。
And the rentier economy just means that
租赁经济只意味着……
if you are young, you can never afford to buy a house.
如果你是年轻人，永远买不起房子。
You can only rent, which means that
你只能租赁，这意味着
you yourself can never go from,
你自己也永远从不…
you have no more social mobility.
你再也没有社会流动性。
So this overall is really bad for America.
因此整体来看，这对美国真的很糟。
Another question then is, how did America get to this point?
另一个问题是， 美国是如何走到这一步的？
How did it transition from a
它是如何从……过渡的？
manufacturing economy to a financial economy?
制造业经济转为金融经济？
And there are different theories out there.
还有各种不同的理论存在。
There are some economists who say that
有些经济学家认为
this is just late -stage capitalism.
这只是后期资本主义而已。
Okay? This is the natural evolution of capitalism.
这就是资本主义的自然演进。
There are some who argue that
有些人认为
it is the neoliberalism or the regular revolution that caused this.
是新自由主义或常规革命导致的。
Okay? When you take government, when you cut back the role of government,
好的？当你削减政府、缩小政府角色时，
when you emphasize free markets, then
当你强调自由市场时，
you have this situation.
你现在有这种情况。
The over -financialization of the economy.
经济的过度金融化。
Okay? What I want to show you today is
好的？我今天想给你展示的是
that you can't just buy a house and you can't just buy a house and you can't just buy a house and you can't just buy a house and you can't just buy a house. The real reason is the transition to empire.
你只买房子就能解决问题的想法是错的，真正原因是转向帝国。
Okay? There's a really simple explanation for why this is happening.
好吧？这件事发生的原因很简单。
The reason is that after the end of the Cold War,
原因是冷战结束后，
1991, America became a global empire.
1991年，美国成为全球帝国。
It could now set the rules of the game,
它现在可以制定游戏规则。
and it set the rules of the game so that it would always win.
并且它制定了游戏规则，使其始终获胜。
And then all money flowed to America,
随后所有资金流向美国。
which created all these asset bubbles.
这就产生了所有这些资产泡沫。
Okay? So
好吧？
that's the argument I'm making to you today.
这就是我今天要给你们阐述的论点。
Okay? So are we clear about what's happening?
好吧？我们现在对发生的事已经清楚了吗？
Any questions so far? Okay.
到此为止，大家有问题吗？好吧。
Now I want to explain to you how America became an empire.
现在我要向你们解释美国是如何成为帝国的。
In fact, I'm going to explain to you how America became an empire. In fact, the most powerful empire in human history
实际上，我要向你们解释美国是如何成为帝国的。实际上，最强大的帝国在人的历史上。
because even though Rome was powerful, it didn't really control the world.
因为即使罗马强大，却并未真正掌控世界。
Whereas America, the American empire today, controls the entire world.
而如今的美帝国则掌控全世界。
Okay? And so to understand how America became an empire,
好了，接下来我们来看看美国是如何成为帝国的。
you have to go back to the founding of America.
你得回到美国建国之初。
Okay? So in 1776, America declared independence
好吧？于是1776年，美国宣布从英国独立。
from Britain. And at
并且在。
that time, they had something called the Declaration of Independence.
那时，他们有一份叫《独立宣言》的文件。
And the Declaration of Independence,
《独立宣言》这份文件，
if you read the document, it's very clear.
如果你读一遍，内容很清晰。
It's what the founding fathers of America said is that
它就是美国建国之初所说的，即我们在美国创建一个以神为基础的新社会
we are founding a new society in America
我们正在美国创建一个新的社会
based on God.
基于神
Okay? Now, the founding fathers were Christians,
好的？现在，建国之父是基督徒，
but they were special type of Christians who believed in the idea of theism.
但他们是特殊类型的基督徒，信奉有神论的观念。
And deism is the idea that, yes, there is a God,
而自然神论则是指，确有一位神，
and God did create everything,
并且上帝造万物，
but God is not interested in managing human affairs.
但上帝不关心人间事务。
God leaves us alone, which means that
上帝把我们放在一边，意味着……
we as humans are empowered to create the world we want to create.
我们人类有能力创造我们想要的世界。
Okay? And the founding fathers wanted to create
好吧？而建国之父想要创建
a new society based
一个以……为基础的新社会
on the idea of the human structure,
关于人类结构的概念，
the structure of God, okay? And what they believed is that
上帝的结构，好的？他们认为的是
God gave human beings three fundamental rights,
上帝赐予人类三项基本权利，
that all governments must respect, okay? And so
所有政府都必须尊重的，好的？于是
the famous phrase is—do you guys know the famous phrase— 'Life,
那句著名的短语是——你们知道那句著名短语吗——‘生命，’
Liberty, and
自由，和
the Pursuit of happiness.
追求幸福。
That is the mission,
那就是使命，
the purpose of America,
美国的目的。
to ensure that every American would have life,
以确保每个美国人都有生命，
liberty, and the pursuit of happiness.
自由，和追求幸福。
And that's really the goal, the role of government.
这才是目标，政府的角色。
Life, to make you safe,
生命，让你安全，
to provide security against enemies.
提供对敌人的安全保障。
Liberty, the right to say whatever you believe,
自由，能说出你所信的任何话，
the right to believe whatever you believe.
能相信你所信的任何事物。
So the tolerance of all
于是容忍一切
creeds, religions. The last is the pursuit of happiness.
信条、宗教。最后是追求幸福。
What does pursuit of happiness mean?
追求幸福到底是什么？
You guys know? So
你们知道吗？于是
Thomas Jefferson wrote the Declaration of Independence, and
托马斯·杰斐逊写下独立宣言，且
when he wrote the pursuit of happiness, he had a very specific idea in mind.
他写下“追求幸福”时，脑中已有非常具体的想法。
What does the pursuit of happiness mean?
追求幸福到底是什么？
Which is what? Okay, so wealth, okay?
那又是什么？好吧，财富，行吗？
So in America, your fundamental right,
于是在美国，你的基本权利，
the fundamental purpose of your life is to make as much money as you can,
你的生命基本目的就是尽可能多赚钱，
to amass as much wealth as you can, okay?
尽可能多积累财富，好吗？
And the idea here is that in this society,
而这里的想法是，在这个社会里，
in this new societies, there's an experiment called America,
在这新的社会中，有一个叫做美国的实验，
if we allow everyone
如果我们让每个人
to pursue the
去追求
creation of wealth, then
财富的创造，然后
America will become powerful, okay?
美国将变得强大，好吗？
That's the idea. And it turned out that
这就是想法。结果证明
this idea was absolutely correct, okay?
这个想法完全正确，好吗？
In a very short amount of time,
在很短的时间里
America industrialized very rapidly,
美国工业化非常迅速，
and at the end of World War II,
第二次世界大战结束时，
America became the most powerful country in the world,
美国成为世界最强大的国家，好吗？
okay? After World War II,
第二次世界大战后，
it decided that
它决定了
it can now export
它现在可以出口
its philosophy to the rest of the world.
其哲学传递给世界其他地区。
So in 1944, there's something called the Bretton Woods Conference,
于是1944年，出现了一个叫布雷顿森林会议的事件。
okay?
好吗？
And so in 1944, everyone knew that
于是1944年，大家都知道了
Nazi Germany would be defeated, okay?
纳粹德国将被击败，好吗？
And Japan would be defeated, which would make America,
而日本也将被击败，这将使美国，
Japan, would be defeated, which would make America, Japan, would be defeated, which would make America, the most powerful,
日本将被击败，这将使美国……最强大
the richest nation on the planet, okay?
地球上最富裕的国家，好吗？
Now, the Soviet Union was a competitor, but
现在，苏联是竞争者，但
they didn't really matter, okay?
它们并不重要，好吗？
They had their own sphere of influence.
它们各自拥有势力范围。
So America got together with its allies in Europe,
于是美国与欧洲盟友聚首，决定新全球金融体系的样貌。
and they decided what the new global financial system would look like.
随后他们决定新全球金融体系的样貌。
And the idea was that
而想法是
with Bretton Woods, they decided that the US dollar
在布雷顿森林会议上，他们决定美元
would become the global reserve currency,
将成为全球储备货币，
which basically meant that you could buy anything with the US dollar.
这基本意味着你可以用美元买任何东西。
Now, there were some people at Bretton Woods,
现在，布雷顿森林会议上有一些人，
some economists who
一些经济学家
were afraid that
他们担心
this would cause problems, right?
这会造成问题，对吧？
If you have a government which
如果你有一个政府，
was in control of the global reserve currency,
它掌握了全球储备货币，
that would basically make the government God,
那基本就把政府变成了上帝。
right? If they could just print as much money as they wanted,
对吧？如果他们可以随便印制任意数量的钱，
they could become like Midas.
他们就能像米达斯一样。
If they touch something, it would become gold, okay?
只要他们碰到什么，便会变成黄金，对吧？
So some people thought it was dangerous.
于是有人认为这很危险。
And so the compromise is that
于是达成的折中方案是……
the US dollar had to be backed by gold, okay?
美国美元必须以黄金作背书，明白吗？
The gold standard. In other words,
金本位制。换句话说，
the US dollar was basically like a receipt for gold.
美元基本上就是一张金票。
If you had a million dollars, okay, you could go to any American bank
如果你有一百万美元，嗯，你可以去任何美国银行。
and get a million dollars worth of gold for it, okay?
并为此获得一百万美元等值的黄金，明白吗？
Does that make sense? So that's what we call the gold standard.
这样说通吗？这就是我们所说的金本位制。
And for the longest, and so that led,
而且最久的那段时间，因而导致了……
this Bretton Woods system led to
布雷顿-伍德斯体系带来了……
tremendous prosperity in America and in Europe and in Japan, okay?
……在美国、欧洲和日本都取得了巨大的繁荣，明白吗？
Then in 1971,
随后在1971年，
Richard Nixon did something really radical.
理查·尼克松做了一件非常大胆的事。
He basically said we America,
他基本上说我们美国，
we we're gonna go off the gold standard, okay?
我们要把金本位制抛开，明白吗？
Remember that America had spent too much money
记得美国花了太多钱
on the space race, on Vietnam, on domestic expenses,
用于太空竞赛、越南战争和国内开支，
okay? So they needed to transition out of the gold standard.
明白吗？于是他们需要把金本位制转出。
But if you transition out of the gold standard,
但如果你们把金本位制抛开，
then how do you ensure the US dollar is worth something?
那么怎样保证美元有价值呢？
How do you ensure the intricate worth of the US dollar?
怎样保证美元的内在价值呢？
So they transitioned from the gold standard to what?
于是他们从金本位制转向什么？
Do you guys know? Oil, okay, do you understand?
你们知道吗？石油，明白吗？
And that's what we call the petrodollar. And
这就是我们所说的石油美元。并且
the idea here is that, look,
这里的意思是，听着，
every economy needs oil to run, right?
每个经济体都需要石油来运转，对吧？
You need oil as the basis of your economy.
你需要石油作为经济的基础。
And so after America went off the gold standard,
于是美国脱离金本位制后，
these countries in the Middle East, mainly Saudi Arabia, but other countries as well,
这些中东国家，主要是沙特阿拉伯，但也有其他国家，
agreed that you could buy oil using US dollars.
同意用美元买油。
So the idea is, okay, before,
于是想法是，好的，之前，
if you had a million dollars, a million US dollars, you could change,
如果你有一百万美元，你可以把它换成金，
convert that to gold, okay?
把它换成金，好的？
And now you can convert it to oil.
现在你可以把它换成石油。
And this is what we call the petrodollar.
这就是我们所说的石油美元。
And this is really the basis
这才是其根本。
for the value of the US dollar today, okay?
美国美元今天的价值，好的？
So then what happened is that in 1991,
于是发生的事是，1991年，
the Soviet Union fell,
苏联解体。
and now America was in charge of the entire global economy,
现在美国掌控了整个全球经济，
basically, okay? And so America at
基本上，好的？于是美国在那时对大家说，
that time said to everyone, listen, let's focus on trade,
那时大家听好了，先聚焦贸易，
because trade will make everyone rich, okay?
因为贸易会让大家都富裕，好的？
So let me explain the theory of this, okay?
所以让我来解释一下这个理论，好吗？
So America basically wanted everyone to trade.
于是美国基本想让大家都进行贸易。
And the idea of trade, okay, this is like Russia,
再说贸易的概念，好吗？这就像俄罗斯，
this is like China, this is like China, this is like China, this is like America, China, South America.
这像中国，这像中国，这像中国，这像美国，中国，南美。
The idea of trade is that each country
贸易的概念是每个国家……
would focus on its competitive advantage.
将聚焦其竞争优势。
What are you good at? And then
你擅长什么？然后
you would sell this competitive advantage to other countries for what they're good at,
你会把这种竞争优势卖给其他国家，以换取他们擅长的东西，
okay? And the theory here is
好吧？这里的理论是
that if you do it this way,
如果你按这种方式去做，
then all countries will become rich, okay?
那么所有国家都会变得富裕，好吗？
So let me explain why.
好了，我来解释一下原因。
All right, so let's look at, you know, US and China.
好的，那我们来看看美国和中国。
So what China is really good at is cheap labor.
中国真正擅长的是低成本劳动力。
What the United States is really good at is technology.
美国真正擅长的是技术。
The idea is that the United States and China trade.
美国和中国的贸易思路是……
China makes all these cheap goods for American consumers.
中国为美国消费者生产这些低价商品。
But unfortunately,
但不幸的是，
Chinese consumers don't have enough purchasing power to buy American technology.
中国消费者的购买力不足以买得美国技术。
So what happens is that
于是发生的是
America gives China US dollars instead.
美国把美元送给中国。
Trillions and trillions of US dollars.
数万亿美元。
Now, in theory,
理论上，
what's supposed to happen is this money
本来应该发生的是这笔钱
trickles down to the average Chinese.
流入普通中国人手中
So that...
于是…
So that... The average Chinese worker,
于是……普通中国工人，
his wages go up, right?
他的工资上涨了，对吧？
And when his wages go up,
当他的工资上涨时，
what he can do now is buy US products like iPhones.
他现在能做的就是买美国产品，比如iPhone。
And so over time, trade evens out.
于是随着时间推移，贸易就会平衡。
Does that make sense? That's a theory.
这样说对吗？这就是一个理论。
That's the first theory.
第一条理论是这样。
The second theory is how capital moves.
第二条理论是资本如何流动。
And the idea here is that
这里的想法是……
capital is going to go to places.
资本正往各地流动。
Which allows it to grow the most.
这让它增长最快。
Okay? And so the idea is that when
于是，想法是……
you have a globalized world, then
你们有一个全球化的世界，随后
what happens is capital from the United States moves to China.
结果就是美国的资本流向中国。
Right? Because if you invest in China, your capital grows the most.
对吧？因为如果你在中国投资，你的资本增长最快。
You can buy a million dollar house in the United States.
你可以在美国买一栋价值一百万美元的房子。
Or you can buy ten houses for the same money in China.
或者你可以用同样的钱在中国买十栋房子。
So you're better off buying houses in China, right?
所以用钱买房子在中国更划算，对吧？
Okay? So these are the two theories.
好的？所以这就是两种理论。
One is that trade will make everyone rich.
一种是贸易会让每个人都变得富裕。
And second is that
第二种是……
capital will move from rich countries to poor countries.
资本会从富国流向贫国。
Okay? And when you actually go to university and
好？当你真正去大学学习经济学时，像杰克·沃尔夫一样。
you study economics, like Jack Wolfe,
then you actually have to learn these theories.
然后你实际上需要学习这些理论。
But in reality,
但在现实中，
these two theories aren't true.
这两种理论并不成立。
Okay? Okay? Why not?
好？好？为什么不呢？
Why not? Why aren't these two theories true?
为什么不呢？这两种理论为什么不成立？
So the first theory is that
所以第一个理论是……
if two countries trade, over time,
如果两国进行贸易，随着时间推移，
wealth trickles down to everyone in
财富会渗透到该国的每个人身上，
that country, which makes everyone richer.
从而使每个人都更富裕。
Okay? Is that true for China?
好？这对中国成立吗？
No, it's not. Okay? Workers' wages have not gone up for the past 30, 40 years.
不，成立。好？过去三四十年工薪没有上涨。
Why? Because of the idea of elite capture.
为什么？因为精英俘获的想法。
Elite capture. So
精英俘获。于是
all the money is captured by an elite group of people.
所有的钱都被一群精英俘获。
When that happens, okay, they can't spend it.
当那种情况发生时，好吧，他们就没法花了。
They can't buy U.S. goods, right?
他们买不到美国产品，对吧？
So the only thing they can do is invest it.
于是他们唯一能做的就是投资。
Right? Now, according to this theory,
对吧？按这个理论来讲。
they should invest it back in China because
他们应该把钱再投回中国，因为
if you invest it in China, right?
如果你把钱投回中国，对吧？
China should allow for more growth than investment anywhere else.
中国应该比其他地方更能让投资增长。
Okay? But in reality, where do they put their money?
好的？但实际上他们把钱放在哪里？
In the United States. And why would they do that?
在美国。那他们为什么要这么做？
Why? Exactly.
为什么？正是如此。
Okay? You don't put your money where you make the most money.
好的？你把钱投在最能赚的钱上。
You put your money where it's the most safe.
你把钱投在最安全的钱上。
Okay? That's why we have banks. So
好的？这就是我们有银行的原因。
because the United States controls the U.S.
因为美国掌握了美国本土的经济。
economy. The United States controls the U.S. dollar. And because
美国掌握了美元。并且因为
people's wealth is expressed in U.S.
人们的财富以美元计价。
dollars, it makes the most sense to put your money in the United States.
美元，投在美国最有意义。
Okay? And this is not just true for China.
好吧？这不只是中国的情况。
It's true for most countries in the world.
这对世界大多数国家都成立。
And that's why starting in the 90s,
于是从90年代开始，
you have all this wealth amassing in the United States.
你在美国积累了这笔财富。
Okay? Does that make sense? So
好吧？这样说通吗？
everything in the United States became overpriced.
一切在美国都被高估。
Everything. Everything became a speculative bubble.
一切都成了投机泡沫。
Okay? So let me give you an example.
好吧？让我给你举个例子。
Let's look at equities.
让我们看看股票。
Okay? Start market. Stocks.
好吧？开始市场。股票。
In the year 1900, okay?
在1900年，好吧？
In the year 1900, if you look at all the world's stock markets,
在1900年，如果你查看全世界的股票市场，
the largest was the U.K.
最大的就是英国。
Okay? Because obviously the U.K.
好吧？因为显然是英国。
is the most powerful country in the world.
是世界上最强大的国家。
It was the most powerful country at that time.
那时它是最强大的国家。
Sorry. At that time, the U.K.
抱歉，那时英国是最强大的国家。
was the most powerful country. Okay?
是最强大的国家。好吧？
So in a stock market, as a percentage of the entire world, the U.K.
在股票市场中，按全世界比例，英国占约25%。
was the most powerful country. And the entire global stock market was about 25%.
是最强大的国家。全世界股票市场约占25%。
Okay? 24 to 25%.
好的？24%到25%。
The United States was second at 14.5%.
美国排第二，14.5%。
And you had Germany,
还有德国，
about 13%.
约13%。
France at 11%.
法国占11%。
Okay? So that was the situation of wealth in the year 1900.
好吧？那就是1900年的财富分布情况。
And this makes sense. Right? These four countries are industrially extremely powerful.
这也很合理。对吧？这四个国家工业上极其强大。
Today, okay?
今天，好吗？
Today. The year 2024.
今天。2024年。
The United States has 60%
美国拥有60%。
of all the world's stock wealth.
全世界股票财富的60%。
Okay? Who's second?
好？第二名是谁？
Can you guys guess? Who would be second?
你们能猜到吗？谁会排第二？
Japan. Okay?
日本。好吗？
And what is the percentage of global stock wealth?
全球股票财富的百分比是多少？
Can you guys guess? A number?
你们能猜到吗？一个数字？
United States has 66%.
美国拥有66%。
60%. How much does Japan have?
60%。日本有多少？
Can you guess the number? 10% is a good guess, right?
你能猜到数字吗？10%是个不错的猜测，对吧？
It's actually 6%. Okay?
实际上是6%。好吗？
Do you see the disparity? Number one is 60%.
你看到了差距吗？第一名是60%。
Japan, number two, is 6%.
日本，第二位，6%。
It's huge disparity.
差距很大。
How much is China? The world's second largest economy?
中国是多少？世界第二大经济体？
3%. 3%. 3%. Do you understand?
3%。3%。3%。你明白了吗？
All right? So, all this wealth that's being generated around the world,
好了？所以，全球产生的这笔财富，
it can only end up one place.
它最终只能落到一个地方。
Okay? The United States.
好的？美国。
All right? So,
好了？所以，
you have... And
你有……
that's what's pushed the
那就是推动了美国的金融化。
financialization of the U.S.
金融化的美国经济。
economy. Okay? Because this wealth goes to the United States.
好的？因为这笔财富落到美国。
And someone has to pay for it. Someone has to manage this wealth.
有人要为此付费。有人要管理这笔财富。
And this is the financial services sector.
这就是金融服务业。
So, people on Wall Street, and this is very important, people on Wall Street,
于是，华尔街的人们，这一点很重要，华尔街的人们。
they make their money based on how they manage this wealth,
他们的收益取决于他们如何管理这笔财富，
not on whether or not they make money out of this money.
而非取决于他们是否从这笔钱中赚取利润。
Do you understand? They charge a management fee.
你明白吗？他们收取管理费。
Okay? So, in other words,
好的？所以，换句话说，
they're not actually incentivized to be concerned.
他们并不真正被激励去关心。
They're not actually incentivized to be conservative and make sure that this money grows.
他们并不真正被激励去保守，确保这笔钱增长。
What they're incentivized to do is design riskier
他们被激励去设计更具风险的
and riskier assets
更具风险的资产
and
和
investment opportunities to attract more investment,
吸引更多投资的投资机会
because then they can take a management fee, a cut.
因为这样他们就能收取管理费，分成。
Okay? Does that make sense? And that's what's led to so
好吧？这样说通吗？这就是导致……的原因。
much financial over speculation over the past 20 years in the U.S.
过去20年美国经济中出现了大量金融过度投机。
economy. And that's what's led to so much financial over speculation over investment opportunities And
这就是导致大量金融过度投机的原因。
one of America's biggest problems
美国最大的问题之一
is the growing national debt.
是不断增长的国债
Okay? So, the government is paying for a lot of government services just by putting money.
好的？所以，政府只要投入资金就能支付大量政府服务。
Okay? So, right now, the U.S.
好的？现在，美国……
national debt is about $34 trillion.
国债约为34万亿美元。
Okay? And this $34 trillion debt,
好？这34万亿美元的国债，
half of it is owned by foreigners.
其中一半由外国人持有。
Okay? So, Japan has about a trillion.
好的？所以，日本约有一万亿美元。
China has about $800 billion.
中国约有八百亿美元。
So, they buy U.S. treasuries.
于是他们买美国国债。
Okay? So, America owes Japan a trillion dollars.
好？美国欠日本一万亿美元。
America owes China $800 billion.
美国欠中国八百亿美元。
And then half of it, the government owes to its people.
然后其中一半，政府欠自己的人民。
So, the two largest expenses are the military and the pension system.
于是，最大的两项支出是军费和养老金。
Okay? So,
好？于是，
$34 trillion is a lot of money.
三四万亿美元是大笔钱。
Okay? And the U.S. GDP is about $100 trillion.
好？美国的国内生产总值约为100万亿美元。
So, the total debt is about a third of America's GDP.
于是，总债务约占美国国内生产总值的三分之一。
And this debt has interest. So,
而且这笔债务还要付利息。
this debt is growing about $1 to $2 trillion every two to three months.
这笔债务每两到三个月增长约1到2万亿美元。
Okay? And all this is saying, okay, these numbers,
好？而且这些数字说明，好的，这些数字，
all they're telling us is there's absolutely no way
他们告诉我们的就是完全没有办法。
that America can pay all this debt.
那美国能偿还这笔债务。
Okay? So, then the question then is,
好？于是，接下来的问题是，
if you're China and you're Japan,
如果你是中国或日本，
why do you have all this debt knowing that America can never pay you back?
为什么你们会有这么多债务，知道美国永远付不回来？
Or America will at some point default on this debt. Why?
或者美国在某个时点会违约。为什么？
Why does America, why does Japan and China and other countries have all this debt,
为什么美国、为什么日本、中国和其他国家会有这么多债务？
U.S. treasuries? Knowing that
美国国债？知道美国永远付不回来。
America can never really pay back all this debt.
为什么？好。于是，原因有很多。
Why? Okay. So, there are many reasons.
好？
Okay? The first reason is that in theory,
好的？第一原因是理论上，
Japan and China can always take this debt
日本和中国总能用这笔债务买油。
and buy oil with it.
and buy oil withit.
Okay? So, this is again the petrodollar.
好的？所以，这又是石油美元。
Okay? Okay.
好的？好的。
So, the second reason is that even
所以，第二个原因是……
though America's in debt, it's still an empire.
虽然美国负债，却仍是帝国。
It's still the greatest military power in the world.
它仍是世界最大的军力。
So, at some point, you feel that the money is safe there.
于是，你会觉得钱在那里安全。
Okay? Does that make sense? Because no one can actually challenge America militarily.
好的？这样说通吗？因为没人能真正用军力挑战美国。
And the third reason, and this is the most important reason is,
第三个原因，也是最重要的原因是，
there's no place for you to go.
你没有地方可去。
You understand? What else?
你明白了吗？还有什么？
What else? What else? So, where else can you put your money?
还有什么？还有什么？那么，你还能把钱放在哪里？
Nowhere. Okay? So, that's the issue right now.
没有地方。好吧？这就是现在的问题。
And so, in theory, because
于是，理论上，因为
China and
中国和
Japan can buy oil with it,
日本可以用它买油，
and because
并且因为
there's really no place for China and
中国和日本真的没有地方可以放这笔钱，理论上，这个系统可以一直持续下去。
Japan to put this money, in theory, this system can go on forever.
Okay? So, it's possible that
好的？所以，可能会出现……
maybe in 10 years' time, the debt will go away.
也许在十年后，债务会消失。
It will be $340 trillion.
它将达到340万亿美元。
Okay? Who knows? Okay? So, in theory, this could go on forever.
好的吗？谁知道？好的吗？所以，理论上，这可以一直持续下去。
Right? Because America's an empire.
对吗？因为美国是一个帝国。
But then, what happened two,
但随后，发生了两件事。
three years ago is Russia invaded Ukraine.
三年前，俄罗斯入侵乌克兰。
Okay? Russia invaded Ukraine.
好的吗？俄罗斯入侵乌克兰。
And why this is important is
而这件事重要的原因是…
that this is basically Russia challenging China.
那就是俄罗斯在挑战中国。
Why? Because Russia is challenging the dominance of the American empire.
为什么？因为俄罗斯正在挑战美国帝国的主导地位。
Okay? What Putin is really saying to the United States is,
好的吗？普京真正对美国说的是，
I think your empire is full of lies.
我觉得你的帝国充满了谎言。
Your empire is based on nothing.
你的帝国根本无物。
Your empire is based on the perception that you are invincible in war.
你的帝国建立在你在战争中无敌可战的观念上。
Well, I'm going to invade Ukraine and prove everyone wrong.
好吧，我要进攻乌克兰，证明大家都错了。
Okay? I'm going to show that you, America, are in fact a paper tiger.
好的，我要证明美国其实是纸老虎。
Okay? And so,
好的，接下来是……
if Putin succeeds in his war in Ukraine,
如果普京在乌克兰战争中成功，
then the fundamental understanding of how the world works,
那么世界运作的根本理解将会改变，
that America is an empire, that America is invincible,
美国是帝国、美国是无敌可战的观念。
that the U.S. dollar is safe, will radically change.
美元安全的概念将被彻底改变。
It will be destroyed.
它将被摧毁。
It will be undermined. It will be subverted.
它将被削弱并被颠覆。
Okay? Does that make sense? So,
好的？这样说通吗？所以，
that's why America needs
这就是美国需要的原因
to stop Russia in Ukraine.
在乌克兰阻止俄罗斯
Okay? Can it stop Russia in Ukraine?
好的？它能在乌克兰阻止俄罗斯吗？
How's the war going for America in Ukraine?
乌克兰的战争对美国来说进展如何？
Pretty badly. Okay?
相当糟糕。好吧？
I mean, the war is almost over.
我的意思是，战争快结束了。
Okay. So, but
好的。那样，然而
what America can do,
美国可以做的事
okay, which will solve all these problems,
好的，这将解决所有这些问题，
is for America to transition from a financial system to a political system.
美国从金融体系转向政治体系是关键。
Okay? So, America can transition from a financial economy back to a manufacturing economy.
好的？那么，美国可以把金融经济转回制造业经济。
Okay? If America just does this, America has nothing to worry about.
好的？只要美国这么做，便无须再担忧。
It doesn't have to worry about the debt. It doesn't have to worry about Russia.
它不必担心债务，也不必担心俄罗斯。
It doesn't even have to worry about the world.
它甚至不必担心世界。
Okay? Because America is a self -sufficient economy,
好的？因为美国是自给自足的经济体，
meaning that it has the resources to sustain itself.
意味着它拥有维持自身所需的资源。
It doesn't really need to trade with the rest of the world. Okay?
它不必真的与世界其他地方进行贸易。
If America can return to
如果美国能回到
being a manufacturing economy,
成为制造业经济体，
then it can also be a self -sufficient Then it will be invincible.
然后它也可以自给自足，随后就会无敌可战。
Okay? Now, the question then is,
好的？现在，问题是，
can America re -industrialize?
美国能否再工业化？
Yes or no? Why not, Jack?
是还是不是？为什么不行，杰克？
Because the politics doesn't allow them to.
因为政治不允许他们这么做。
Because the politics does not allow them to.
Exactly. But can you explain that?
完全正确。你能解释一下吗？
Like, the financial system has, you know, incredible power.
比如说，金融体系拥有，你知道，惊人的力量。
There's all these countries that need to be a perpetual system.
还有很多国家需要保持这种持续的体系。
And the economy is a perpetual system.
而经济也是一个永续的体系。
Yeah. And they won't allow America to do that.
是的。它们也不让美国这么做。
That's exactly right, Jack. Okay?
正是如此，杰克。好了？
So, yes, the problem right now is the very structure of American society
于是，当前问题正是美国社会结构本身
and politics and the economy.
以及政治和经济。
Right now, the financial sector has all the power.
现在，金融部门拥有全部力量。
And they don't want to go back to the time when manufacturing had all the power.
而他们又不想回到制造业拥有全部力量的时代。
Right? So, that's the first problem.
对吗？所以，那是第一个问题。
But let's just say, for the sake of argument, that they agree to this.
但我们先假设，出于论证之便，大家都同意这一点。
Okay? What's your other problem?
好的？你还有什么问题？
If you want to re -industrialize?
如果你想再工业化？
. Excuse me?
请问一下？
. Okay.
好的。
But all the foreign investment can just go into factories.
但所有外资都可以直接投入工厂。
Right? But there's actually a really big problem with re -industrialization.
对吧？但再工业化确实有个大问题。
Okay? So, as Jack says, there will be political,
好吧？正如杰克所说，接下来会有政治…
you know, political, you know, political resistance to this.
你知道，政治，你知道，政治抵抗。
Okay? But then you have a bigger problem than this, which is what?
好吧？但随后你会有更大的问题，那是什么？
. Okay, guys.
. 好的，大家。
The problem with this economy is it creates a speculative mindset.
这个经济的难点在于它产生了投机心态。
Okay? So, therefore, no one wants to work hard.
好的？所以，结果就是没人想再辛苦工作。
No one wants to go to work in factories anymore.
没人想再去工厂工作了。
Do you understand? If you're a young person,
你明白吗？如果你是个年轻人，
you would much rather spend your time investing
你更愿意把时间投入投资
in Bitcoin than working in a factory.
比在工厂工作更好。
Do you understand? Because
你明白吗？因为
investing in Bitcoin gives you the opportunity to become rich.
投资比特币能让你变得富有。
But if you work in a factory,
但如果你在工厂工作，
you have to work hard for 40 years just to buy a house.
你得辛苦工作四十年才买得一房。
Okay? Does that make sense? So, you're not going to find people to work these factories.
好的？这样说通吗？所以你找不到人来操作这些工厂。
That's a bigger problem. Okay?
这更是个大问题。好吗？
And the third problem, of course, is just investment.
第三个问题当然是投资。
How do you...
你是怎么做的……
How do you build these factories?
你是怎么建造这些工厂的？
You not only have to build these factories, but
你不仅要建造这些工厂，还要……
you also have to build logistics networks to move goods from one place to the next.
你还得建造物流网络，把货物从一个地方运到另一个地方。
Okay? So, in other words,
好的？换句话说，
America could be industrialized, but it's a pain in the ass.
美国可以工业化，但这是一件麻烦事。
Right? You're going to face a lot of political opposition,
对吧？你将面临大量政治阻力，
especially from the financial sector.
尤其来自金融部门。
It's very hard for you to get people to work in factories.
对你来说，让人们在工厂工作很难。
And plus, where's all this money going to come from?
再说，这笔钱从哪儿来？
Okay? So,
好吧？那么，
if you can't beat Russia in Ukraine, and
如果你在乌克兰不能打败俄罗斯，且
if you can't re -industrialize, then
如果你不能再工业化，那么
what can you do to protect the petrodollar
你能做什么来保护石油美元
and your financial system?
以及你的金融体系？
Well, I have an idea. Okay?
我有个主意。
Invade Iran. Okay?
入侵伊朗。好吧？
Invade Iran. Now, why would you do that?
入侵伊朗。现在，为什么要这么做？
Okay? And the answer is that, unfortunately,
好吧？答案是，遗憾地说，
of all the options out there, okay,
在所有可选方案中，先说一下，
because America can't just sit back and let its empire collapse, right?
因为美国不能只是坐着等帝国崩溃，对吧？
Of all the options out there,
在所有可选方案中，
invading Iran happens to be politically the easiest to do.
入侵伊朗恰好是最容易的政治手段。
Okay? You're not...
好吧？你还不是……
You can't go fight a war against Russia because Russia has nuclear weapons.
你不能去跟俄罗斯打一场战争，因为俄罗斯有核武器。
You cannot re -industrialize because there'll be too much political opposition towards that.
你无法再工业化，因为会有太多政治反对。
Plus, it'll take you about 50 years to re -industrialize.
再加上，重新工业化大约需要五十年。
But if you invade Iran,
但如果你入侵伊朗，
well, you accomplish three things.
好吧，你完成了三件事。
Okay? The first thing is you show the world
好吧？第一件事是你向世界展示
that you're still the top dog.
你依旧是顶尖。
Your military is still invincible.
你的军队仍然无敌可战
Okay? So, you're a foreign investor in America.
好的？所以，你是美国的外资投资者。
You have a trillion US dollars.
你有一万亿美元。
You feel safe.
你觉得安全。
Okay? You don't think the US dollar will collapse.
好吧？你认为美元不会崩溃。
Okay? That's the first thing.
好吧？那是第一件事。
To show the world that America is still the best.
向世界展示美国依旧是最好的。
To show the world the world's foremost military power.
向世界展示世界最强的军事实力。
Therefore, the US dollar is safe.
因此，美元是安全的。
Okay? Second is oil,
好吧？第二个是油。
right? What is the US dollar based on?
对吧？美元是基于什么的？
Oil, right? Well, if you control oil,
油，对吗？那么，如果你掌握了油，
then you don't have to worry about people abandoning the US dollar.
然后你就不必担心人们放弃美元了。
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay?
好吧？这有道理吗？好吧？
And it happens that the Middle East produces...
并且中东产油量占全球的40%。
40% of the world's oil.
And Iran is the world's fourth largest oil exporter.
伊朗是世界第四大油出口国。
But when you take over Iran, you also control Iraq as well.
但当你接管伊朗时，也就掌握了伊拉克。
You control that entire area.
你控制那整个区域。
Okay? And the third thing about invading Iran is trade.
好吧？再说，入侵伊朗的第三点是贸易。
Okay? So,
好吧？那么，
that area, most of the world's trade has to pass through that area.
那片区域，全球大部分贸易都要经过那里。
Right? So, invading Iran would allow you to control the world's shipping lanes.
对吗？所以，入侵伊朗就能让你掌握全球航运通道。
Okay? So,
好吧？那么，
that would be the theory behind invading Iran.
那就是入侵伊朗的理论依据。
Okay? But
好吧？但
the motivation would be
动机将是
to save the American empire.
拯救美国帝国
Because if Putin wins in Ukraine,
因为如果普京在乌克兰赢了，
then America is going to look weak.
于是美国将显得弱小。
It's going to look like a paper tiger.
看起来像只纸老虎。
Okay? And in this situation, as the empire,
好吧？而在这种情况下，作为帝国，
you have to act.
你得行动。
Today, you have a lot of countries in Africa
今天，你在非洲有许多国家
who are rebelling against the Western powers.
谁在对抗西方大国。
France, basically, and America.
法国，基本上，和美国。
Why? Because they think that Putin is now in charge.
为什么？因为他们认为普京现在掌权。
Okay? Why did October 7th...
好吧？10月7日为什么会发生…
Why did Hamas attack Israel?
为什么哈马斯袭击以色列？
I guarantee you that if it were not for the war in Ukraine,
我保证你，如果不是乌克兰战争，
Hamas would not have done such a thing.
哈马斯本不会做出这件事。
Okay? For the longest time before the war in Ukraine,
好吧？在乌克兰战争之前的很长一段时间里。
there was a perception in the world
世界上曾有一种观念
that America was militarily invincible.
美国在军事上无敌可战
No power,
无势力
no country could ever dare stand up against the United States.
没有任何国家敢对美国起而立
And by invading Ukraine, Putin has proved everyone wrong.
并且通过入侵乌克兰，普京证明了大家的错误。
Okay? The United States can be defeated.
好吧？美国可以被击败。
And so what the United States must do now is prove to the world,
于是美国现在必须做的事是向世界证明，
nope, we're still militarily the greatest power in the world.
没错，我们仍然是世界上最强大的军事力量。
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay?
好吧？这样说通吗？好吧？
And again, it must do
再一次，它必须做到。
so to protect its financial economy.
为此，保护其金融经济。
Otherwise, there's a very good chance
否则，出现很好的机会
that this financial economy will implode onto itself.
这个金融经济将会自我崩溃。
Okay? If China,
好吧？如果中国、
Japan, other countries pull out of the war, they will be able to do so.
日本、其他国家退出战争，他们就能做到。
If they pull out of the U.S.
如果他们退出美国
financial sector, okay? If they sell the U.S. treasuries,
金融部门，好吗？如果他们卖掉美国国债，
not only will America
不只是美国
face a sovereign debt crisis,
将面临主权债务危机
but it will lose access to easy money.
但它将失去易钱的渠道。
Okay? Easy money. And
好吧？易钱。还有
the problem in America today is that
美国今天的问题是
America is an empire addicted to easy money.
美国是一个沉迷于易钱的帝国。
Okay? People are so used to just sitting around
好的？人们已经习惯了只坐着发百万美元
and making millions of dollars that
they cannot imagine or tolerate a day when they have to go back to working hard.
他们想不出来也想不住得
Okay? So it's this addiction to easy money
好吧？这就是对易钱的沉迷
which will drive American,
这将驱使美国人
which will drive America to invade Iran.
这将驱使美国去入侵伊朗
Okay? Does that make sense? Okay, any questions?
好的？这样说通吗？好，问个问题吗？
..
…
...
............
......
.. managed okay so this is actually very complicated okay because
.. 已经处理好，好的，这实际上很复杂，好因为
again the financial sector is very large but
再次，金融业非常庞大，但
if you have us dollars then
如果你手里有美元的话
your options are you can invest in the stock
你的选择是：可以投资股市；可以投资房市；今天的问题是…
market you can invest in um houses okay the problem today is
因为世界上有太多富豪了。
because there are too many rich people in the world
and
和
all this money is going to america all assets are bubbles now okay
所有这笔钱都流向美国，所有资产现在都是泡沫，好吧
so the irony of all this is that
于是这件事的讽刺之处在于
you feel that
你觉得……
your only option is to invest in america but but when
你的唯一选择是投资美国，但当……
you do this you're actually losing value okay
你这么做时实际上是在失去价值
and that's why the system is not really sustainable everyone's going to america
于是这就是系统不太可持续的原因，大家都去美国
and that's driving up all these asset prices but
于是这又把所有资产价格推高了，但
in the long term that
从长远来看……
will destroy the american economy in the long term um it'll create all these bubbles
将会在长期内摧毁美国经济，随后会产生一连串泡沫
that will destroy that will also destroy individual wealth okay does that
这将会摧毁并且还会摧毁个人财富，行吗？
make sense any more questions so
还有问题吗？
like if america reaches the war
如果美国赢得战争
in iran like other countries
在伊朗以及其他国家
will be even more confident in america
将更有信心
okay so so so
好的，好的，好的
so jack asked a great question which
于是杰克提出了一个很好的问题，
is like listen if going to if going to
就是听着，如果去……
iran is all about restoring confidence
伊朗就是要恢复对美国的信心
in the united states well if america loses the war
如果美国输掉战争
then that would destroy even more confidence okay
那就会更进一步破坏信心
and so
和所以
this is this is the problem of empires
这就是帝国的难题
empires have something called hubris right imperial hubris
帝国有一种叫做帝国自大之气的东西
which means that
这意味着
they cannot imagine the possibility
他们无法想象失去战争的可能性
of losing a war okay
of losing a warokay
so why is that okay there are two reasons okay there are two reasons the first reason is
所以为什么可以，原因有两个，第一点是
that an empire what an empire is it is a war it's it's a force
一个帝国是什么，它是一场战争，是一种力量
that imposes reality onto others okay an empire makes you see the world
它把现实强加给别人，帝国让你看到世界
the way the empire wants you to see the world okay does
帝国想让你看到的世界方式，好的，明白了
that make sense which means there's no feedback loop which means
这有道理吗？这意味着没有反馈回路，意味着……
that you cannot actually tell the empire what you think it doesn't
你实际上无法告诉帝国你的想法，它不……
your voice doesn't matter which means that
你的声音不重要，这意味着……
an empire it's not possible for an empire to imagine
一个帝国不可能想象……
the possibility of it ever collapsing you understand
它有可能崩溃，你懂了
if it could it would never collapse okay that's the first problem second problem is
如果它能做到，它就永不崩溃——这就是第一个问题；第二个问题是……
that okay let's do a thought experiment
好了，先做个思考实验
if you had a choice if you had a choice would you rather be smart
如果你有选择，你会更愿意做聪明且有策略的，还是傲慢且愚蠢的？
and strategic or stupid and
和战略性或愚蠢且自大…
arrogant if you had a
如果你有一个…
choice in in an ideal world would you would you rather be smart
选择在理想世界里，你会更愿意…
and strategic or stupid and
和战略性或愚蠢且自大…
arrogant okay the answer is stupid
傲慢，好的答案是愚蠢的…
and arrogant because it makes you feel good okay stupid people
和傲慢，因为它让你觉得好，好的愚蠢人…
feel good about themselves right smart people
感觉好，自己很聪明的人
get depressed they doubt themselves they question themselves
他们会沮丧，怀疑自我，问自己问题
and that makes you feel bad most people in an ideal world
这让人感觉糟糕，理想世界里的人们
would want to feel good about themselves always okay
想让自己一直觉得好，没错吧
so it so when
于是如此，接着说
you are an empire you want to be stupid and arrogant
当你是一个帝国时，你想要愚蠢且傲慢
because it makes you feel good it doesn't make sense okay
因为它让你觉得好，它不太合理，好的吧
but that's why empires collapse because you're not going to be able to do what you want once they have too much power they become stupid
但正是因为如此，帝国才会崩溃：当你拥有过多的力量时，你会变得愚蠢且傲慢，失去考虑可能性的能力
and arrogant and they refuse to consider the possibility
and arrogant and they refuseto consider the possibility
that they could be wrong okay does that
那他们可能错了，行吗？
make sense jack okay any more questions
有道理吗，杰克？还有问题吗？
okay uh the american empire has been building for a long time okay
美国帝国已经建造很久了，行吗？
so you can make the argument that the empire really started after after World War II,
于是你可以说，帝国真正开始于二战之后，
because now America controlled half the world, and
因为那时美国掌控了世界一半，
then it became dominant after the end of the Cold War, when the Soviet Union collapsed.
随后在冷战结束、苏联崩溃后又成为主导。
And at that time, okay, before the collapse of the Cold War,
在那时，行吧，冷战崩溃之前，
America had to behave itself.
美国必须自我安排。
And the reason it had to behave itself was it wasn't afraid of the Soviet Union,
之所以要自我安排，是因为它不怕苏联。
it was afraid of communism, right?
它害怕共产主义，对吧？
That's why from 1950 to 1980, they treat their workers
这就是为什么从1950到1980年，他们对工人如此照顾，
so well, because they were afraid of a worker revolt, right?
因为他们害怕工人起义，对吧？
So the real threat was not the Soviet Union, the real threat was communism
于是真正的威胁不是苏联，而是共产主义
as an opposing ideology to capitalism.
作为对资本主义的对立意识形态
Unfortunately today, there's no opposing ideology towards capitalism,
可惜如今对资本主义已无对立意识形态
okay? And that's why America can do what it wants.
好的？这就是美国能随心所欲的原因。
It does not fear any enemies, it does not fear internal revolt.
它不怕任何敌人，也不怕内部起义。
Okay, does that make sense? Okay, all right, so I'll see you guys next week. Bye.
好，听得懂吧？好了，周末见。再见。